<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Orpheus his iourney to hell and his musicke to the ghosts]</title>
            <author>R. B., fl. 1595.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1595</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00464</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1060</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110414</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845964</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845964</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10897</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00464)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10897)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 195:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[Orpheus his iourney to hell and his musicke to the ghosts]</title>
                  <author>R. B., fl. 1595.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24+] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>R. Johnes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1595]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Author's initials from STC.</note>
                  <note>Title and imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: B-D⁴+.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; lacks all before quire B and D4 torn affecting text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Orpheus (Greek mythology) --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:10897:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10897:1"/>
            <head>ORPHEVS His lourney to Hell</head>
            <lg>
               <l>WHen as the world in her firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>olden time,</l>
               <l>frutefull in cuerie bleſſing did abound:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Floras</hi> pride was alwaies in her prime,</l>
               <l>and Winters wrath did ner' offend the ground</l>
               <l>But without labour euery thing encreaſed,</l>
               <l>And pleaſant ſommers ſeaſons neuer ceaſed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No harſh aſpect of heauens reſtleſſe frame</l>
               <l>did alter earthly creatures in their kinde:</l>
               <l>Each ſauage beaſt and bird that time was tame,</l>
               <l>and all the world accorded in one minde.</l>
               <l>For then diſſention was a thing vnknowne,</l>
               <l>And ſeedes of enuie and debate not ſowne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When as olde <hi>Saturne</hi> had in peace diſpoſed,</l>
               <l>his ſeepter and his glorious throne in heauen:</l>
               <l>And in their ſeuerall kingdome had incloſed,</l>
               <l>each of his children and by portions euen,</l>
               <l>Making all ſeueral kings in ſeuerall places,</l>
               <l>Deuided to them all his giftes and graces.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then did great <hi>Ioue</hi> in peace ſucceede his Sire,</l>
               <l>and <hi>Neptune</hi> bridled in the lawleſle ſeas:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pluto</hi> in hell amidſt a world of fire,</l>
               <l>keeping tormented ſoules from reſt and eaſe,</l>
               <l>Orerules the hagges that in thoſe dungeons moyles,</l>
               <l>And to the Ghoſts impoſes endleſſe toyles.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:10897:2"/>
            <lg>
               <l>In this contented time was <hi>Orpheus</hi> borne,</l>
               <l>compoſ'd of purer mettell than a man:</l>
               <l>Made mortall by the Gods in Natures ſcorne,</l>
               <l>that earth might witnes how the heauens can</l>
               <l>Incloſe in Elementall ſhapes celeſtiall thinges,</l>
               <l>Whoſe life from quinteſcence of heauen ſprings.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This pure compoſed ſhape the Gods endued</l>
               <l>with their owne vertues, els had it been ſhame,</l>
               <l>That he whoſe bodie from the heauens iſſued,</l>
               <l>ſhould haue a ſoule forg'd in a baſer frame.</l>
               <l>Thus did the Gods agree for to combine</l>
               <l>A heauenly body and a ſoule diuine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This was that <hi>Orpheus,</hi> whoſe delightfull ſtringes,</l>
               <l>drew to their ſiluer ſound the ſenceleſſe trees:</l>
               <l>That ſtill'd the muſicke of the bubbling ſprings,</l>
               <l>and ſtaide the ſtreames to heare his harmonies:</l>
               <l>That made the ſauage beaſts forſake their praie,</l>
               <l>And gently come to heare ſweet <hi>Orpheus</hi> play.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The craggie rockes that walles the Oceans bound,</l>
               <l>where <hi>Neptune</hi> keeps his watrie regiment,</l>
               <l>Roſe from their flinty roots to heare him ſound,</l>
               <l>and whil'ſt he ſang ſeem'd for to ſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d content.</l>
               <l>The fiſhes left the ſeas to liue a ſhore,</l>
               <l>Which neuer heard of Muſicks name before.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus liu'd be long the woonder of his time,</l>
               <l>whoſe heauen-borne muſicke wonne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> loue of all</l>
               <l>Aſpiring honor taught his fame to clime,</l>
               <l>and made him liue ſecure from thought of fall.</l>
               <l>Till Fortune that orerules the ſtate of kinges,</l>
               <l>Did oreturne him, as ſhe doth other things.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:10897:2"/>
            <lg>
               <l>The pleaſiing poyſon of ſelf-killing Loue,</l>
               <l>at laſt made entrance to his mayden-heart:</l>
               <l>Where once being anchored, neuer would remoue,</l>
               <l>but with ſweet tickling wounds there bred his ſmart.</l>
               <l>Yet did his wiſh preuaile, his hope's effected,</l>
               <l>His Loue found loue, and neuer was rejected.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But as it is in things being ſooneſt growne,</l>
               <l>whoſe flowered bloſſoms euery blaſt decayes:</l>
               <l>And neuer ſtayes the Autumne to be mowne,</l>
               <l>but flooriſhes and falles within few dayes:</l>
               <l>So is't in loue, which being quicklie ſproong,</l>
               <l>Dies oftentimes when as it is but yoong.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Euridice,</hi> the flower of flowering <hi>Thrace,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>whom <hi>Orpheus</hi> often in his ditties praiſed,</l>
               <l>She that had all perfection in her fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>and at her face made euery thing amazed:</l>
               <l>For loue of her <hi>Orpheus</hi> incurr'd this paine,</l>
               <l>Though ſhe with loue requited loue againe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Being thus agreed in loue, and both contented,</l>
               <l>the day was pointed for their marriage right:</l>
               <l>When moſt aſſur'd they ſooneſt were preuented,</l>
               <l>and ſundred by vnconſtant Fortunes ſpight.</l>
               <l>So by the meanes of a malignant power,</l>
               <l>Their ioyes began and ended in an hower.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The marriage day being come, and all things fit,</l>
               <l>and <hi>Hymeneus</hi> rites now done and ended:</l>
               <l>Home they returne, and at their banquets ſit,</l>
               <l>with pleaſures ſuch, as to ſuch meetings tended.</l>
               <l>And when at home was ended all their ſport,</l>
               <l>Then to the pleaſant Meades did all reſort.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:10897:3"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Where as the Maides by cuſtome came in thronges,</l>
               <l>when any Maid was married from their traine:</l>
               <l>And there they ſpend the time in ſport and ſongs,</l>
               <l>that other may doe ſo to them againe:</l>
               <l>Where ſome were dancing hand in hand in ringes,</l>
               <l>And others ſit to heare how <hi>Orpheus</hi> ſings.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Here <hi>Orpheus</hi> warbles on his trembling ſtringes,</l>
               <l>for to delight <hi>Euridice</hi> his joy:</l>
               <l>She ſometimes dances, then ſits downe and ſings,</l>
               <l>and woman like begins to kiſſe and toy,</l>
               <l>Thus theſe two ſporting in each others ſight,</l>
               <l>Thinkes euery hower a yeare till it be night.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When as the wearie horſes of the Sunne,</l>
               <l>began to hie them downe vnto their reſt,</l>
               <l>And now their maiſters iourney almoſt done,</l>
               <l>they end their toylſome labour in the weſt:</l>
               <l>Home hies theſe louers with a full intent</l>
               <l>To change theſe ſportes to other merriment.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And as they footed ore the pleaſant meades,</l>
               <l>like to the Huntreſſe, and her maiden traine:</l>
               <l>A Serpent ſliding from amongſt the weeds,</l>
               <l>ſting'd faire <hi>Euridice,</hi> and with that maine</l>
               <l>Expels her ayerie Spirites from the wound,</l>
               <l>And leaues her chill-cold body on the ground.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nor would th'impartiall Deſtinies permit,</l>
               <l>her wofull ſoule to take her laſt adew:</l>
               <l>But greedilie they ſeaze themſelues on it,</l>
               <l>which downe vnto the Stygian ſtreames they drew,</l>
               <l>Where they appointed her for to remaine,</l>
               <l>That ſhe might waight vpon <hi>Proſerpins</hi> traine.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:10897:3"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Which when the <hi>Thracian</hi> Poet had perceiued,</l>
               <l>how ſuddainly <hi>Furidice</hi> was gone:</l>
               <l>With madding furie ſometimes rag'd and raued,</l>
               <l>and then with tragicke tunes begins to mone,</l>
               <l>Sighing that his <hi>Furidice</hi> was dead.</l>
               <l>Before ſhe knew the pleaſure of his bed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ſitting there by her poyſoned wound,</l>
               <l>ſauing the skarlet blood that iſſued foorth,</l>
               <l>Moiſture ouer-deare to dew the ground,</l>
               <l>or quench the thirſt of this vnſatiate earth:</l>
               <l>Wiſhing or ſhe were here with him againe,</l>
               <l>Or he with her in the <hi>Elizian</hi> plaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus till pale death from her vermilion cheekes,</l>
               <l>Had drawne the vntainted mixture of her hue,</l>
               <l>Diſtreſſed <hi>Orpheus</hi> with his ſorrow ſeekes</l>
               <l>her now decaying beautie to renue:</l>
               <l>Till when he ſaw that all his hope was vaine,</l>
               <l>He tooke himſelfe vnto his harpe againe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Where in a mournfull <hi>Anteme</hi> he bewailes</l>
               <l>the ſiniſter occaſion of his birth;</l>
               <l>Till his deuiding voyce with teares now failes,</l>
               <l>and cannot eccho to his other mirth:</l>
               <l>But with ſad lookes and dumbe demeanes he brings,</l>
               <l>His countenance correſpondent to his ſtrings.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Vnto whoſe muſicke flockes the neighboring hilles,</l>
               <l>the ſhadie groues, the pleaſant murmuring ſprings,</l>
               <l>And all the plaines with companie now filles,</l>
               <l>as beaſts and birds, fiſh, foule, and other thinges,</l>
               <l>And when as euery one had tane his ſeat,</l>
               <l>Thus <hi>Orpheus</hi> gius his ſorrowes to repeat.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:10897:4"/>
            <lg>
               <l>You free-borne people, from inthralling bandes</l>
               <l>of libertie, depriuing Loues eſtate:</l>
               <l>Now mutually come all and ioyhe your handes,</l>
               <l>and helpe your <hi>Orpheus</hi> to bewayle his mate.</l>
               <l>Weepe for <hi>Euridice</hi> that loued me well,</l>
               <l>Whoſe beauty now fades and decayes in hell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Vnheady rulers of this wretched clime,</l>
               <l>you Gods I meane, whoſe hands directes our helme,</l>
               <l>Why did you ſort my dayes vnto this time,</l>
               <l>and in this ſea of ſorrow ouerwhelme:</l>
               <l>The proſperous beginning of my life,</l>
               <l>By this vniuſt diuorcing of my wife.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ah could your cruclty inact this deed,</l>
               <l>to mixt ſweet beauty with deformity:</l>
               <l>For all my merites, render you this meed,</l>
               <l>the injurious rape of my <hi>Euridice?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Shall ſhe attend grim <hi>Pluto</hi> in his den,</l>
               <l>That was belou'd of Gods, admir'd of men?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Haſt thou forgot to loue great <hi>Saturnes</hi> ſonne,</l>
               <l>or didſt thou enuie <hi>Orpheus</hi> in his loue?</l>
               <l>Remember how thy ſelfe haſt been orecum,</l>
               <l>leauing the Synode of the Gods aboue,</l>
               <l>To dote on one, whoſe beauties greateſt grace,</l>
               <l>May not compare with ſweet <hi>Euridice</hi> face.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then in remembrance what thou ſometime wert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>ſee the diſtreſt eſtate wherein I am:</l>
               <l>And if it reſt in thee to eaſe my ſmart,</l>
               <l>for pitie, pitie <hi>Orpheus</hi> miſerie:</l>
               <l>And if ſhe haue not paſſ'd the <hi>Stygian</hi> maine,</l>
               <l>Ah, call her backe to liue with me againe.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:10897:4"/>
            <lg>
               <l>So ſhall thy name eterniz'd by my skill,</l>
               <l>be honor'd for this memorable deed:</l>
               <l>And neuer ſhall my warbling harp be ſtill,</l>
               <l>but euery where thy woorthineſſe ſhall ſpred:</l>
               <l>Till by my means the world reſound thy power,</l>
               <l>And thou ſhalt bid me ceaſe and ſing no more.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But if it be too late for to recall her,</l>
               <l>and that already ſhe hath paſſ'd the flood,</l>
               <l>VVhere grieſlie Futies, fiends, and hagges inthrall her,</l>
               <l>whence ſhe can not returne to doe me good:</l>
               <l>Then hence forth ſhall my ſtrings ſurceaſe to ſound,</l>
               <l>And I will leaue to ſing till ſhee be found.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You wofull trees that witneſſe of my mones,</l>
               <l>with hanging tops and teare-diſtilling ſhowes:</l>
               <l>You ſiluer ſtreams, huge hils, hand rockes and ſtones,</l>
               <l>that haue been witneſſe to my weary woes:</l>
               <l>Heer all together take your laſt farewell,</l>
               <l>Your <hi>Orpheus</hi> goes to ſeeke his loue in hell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And if the grieſly furies will attend,</l>
               <l>the mournfull muſicke which meane time Ile make:</l>
               <l>If <hi>Pluto</hi> will but ſuffer the to ſpend</l>
               <l>ſome ſolemne ſonnets for my Loues ſweet ſake,</l>
               <l>Then haply may the gentle Queene of <hi>Dis,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For pitie ſake reſtore me to my bliſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This ſaid, he rouſ'd him from the tender graſſe,</l>
               <l>which mourn'd in Sable to heare <hi>Orpheus</hi> weepe:</l>
               <l>And in a melancholy moode doth paſſe,</l>
               <l>vnto the place that leads downe to the deep,</l>
               <l>VVhere was innumerable ghoſtes before,</l>
               <l>Haſting for paſſage, downe to <hi>Charons</hi> ſhore.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:10897:5"/>
            <lg>
               <l>And through the yrkſome ſhadow of blacke night,</l>
               <l>he treads the fatall way to loath ſome hell,</l>
               <l>By many noyſome vaultes depriu'd of light,</l>
               <l>where none but. Furies, bugs, and torturs dwell.</l>
               <l>Vntill he came downe to the Stygian bankes,</l>
               <l>Where as the ſillie ghoſtes attend in rankes,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There by the ſhore, poore <hi>Orpheus</hi> ſits him down,</l>
               <l>and gins to tune his mournfull inſtrument:</l>
               <l>Whereas the ſoules doe flock about him ſoone,</l>
               <l>to heare the ſequell of this ſtrange euent.</l>
               <l>And he with heauie lookes and countenance pale,</l>
               <l>Recites the proceſſe of our former tale.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus (quoth he) for my Loue haue I for ſooke</l>
               <l>the <hi>Thracian</hi> fieldes and company of men:</l>
               <l>And for her ſake this iourney vndertooke,</l>
               <l>to vgly grim-fac'd <hi>Plutoes</hi> ſmokie den:</l>
               <l>Where if I chance to meet with my delight,</l>
               <l>Theſe paynes will be requited with her ſight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But if I miſſe of my <hi>Euridice,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>and cannot find her out amongſt the fields:</l>
               <l>Which the black Iudges of that monarchie,</l>
               <l>vnto ſuch ſeperated louers yeelds,</l>
               <l>Where they in ſolitarie paſſion ſpend</l>
               <l>Their weary daies, which neuer ſhall haue end.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then will the heauie burthen of diſpaire,</l>
               <l>clog downe my vitall ſpirits to the ground:</l>
               <l>And my poore heart been ſplit in two with care,</l>
               <l>let my poore ſoule eſcape that fatall wound.</l>
               <l>And in that heauie plight poore <hi>Orpheus</hi> ſhall</l>
               <l>Quite looſe his comfort, labor, life and all.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:10897:5"/>
            <lg>
               <l>By this bad <hi>Charon</hi> landed all his freight,</l>
               <l>and ſet them ſafe vpon the other ſhore:</l>
               <l>And with all ſpeed returned thether ſtraight,</l>
               <l>to loade his boate againe, and carie more.</l>
               <l>Where when he ſaw them cluſtering altogether,</l>
               <l>Gan marueil what new ghoſt was the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> come thether.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But when he look'd on <hi>Orpheus,</hi> view'd his face,</l>
               <l>and euery circumſtance had onely ey'd:</l>
               <l>He told him that hee might not paſſe that place,</l>
               <l>and to tranſport him flatlie he deny'd.</l>
               <l>Had not the Poet with a pleaſant ſtraine</l>
               <l>Quench'd the fierce furie of his wrath enflame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then he whoſe eares inur'd to heare the cries</l>
               <l>of painfull ſoules in endleſſe miſeries:</l>
               <l>Whoſe concaue feet and fierie flaming eyes,</l>
               <l>fixt on no ſubject but deformities.</l>
               <l>Amaz'd to heare him ſtand as one that's dead,</l>
               <l>Or chang'd to ſtone at ſight of Gorgons head.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Such was the force of Muſickes Arte in him,</l>
               <l>as tam'd this ſauage brood of helliſh kinde:</l>
               <l>Enchaunted all his bodie lim by lim,</l>
               <l>and turn'd his ſauage vnrelenting mind.</l>
               <l>And where before he kept him from his charge,</l>
               <l>Now he entreats him to accept his barge.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And rowing him ore to the other ſide,</l>
               <l>curteouſly helps to conduct him a ſhore:</l>
               <l>Proteſting ſolemnly vntill that tyde,</l>
               <l>he neuer help'd ſuch paſſengers before.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:10897:6"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Whence <hi>Orpheus</hi> looking to the Sulphuriſh flame,</l>
               <l>and foggy ſmokes aſcending from that pit:</l>
               <l>Oft times repeates his Louers pleaſing name,</l>
               <l>wiſhing himſelfe might by her reſt and ſit,</l>
               <l>Where they with Louers ſongs, and ſweet tun'd rime,</l>
               <l>Might ſpend the courſe of euerlaſting time.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The came he to the ruſtie gates of death,</l>
               <l>whereas the tripple headed porter dwels:</l>
               <l>Who being amaz'd for to ſee him beneath,</l>
               <l>ſends from his hollow throat ſuch thundring yels,</l>
               <l>As ſummon'd all the Furies at his calles,</l>
               <l>To leaues their taskes and haſte vnto the walles.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now in this place no ſuceour doeth remayne,</l>
               <l>to helpe him in or rid him out their clawes:</l>
               <l>Saue for to fall vnto his harpe againe,</l>
               <l>and by that meanes breake ope the brazen jawes</l>
               <l>Of gredie hell, that there in darkneſſe holdes,</l>
               <l>More then large heauen in his compaſſe folds.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then gins the Poet tune his ſiluer ſtrings,</l>
               <l>whoſe heauenly harmony had power to mooue:</l>
               <l>Hilles, trees and ſtones, beaſts, birds, and other things,</l>
               <l>both men on earth, and all the gods aboue,</l>
               <l>To ſee if it would come to this euent</l>
               <l>Mongſt the black people of this regiment.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You that doe triumph ouer Deaths ſucceſſe,</l>
               <l>and in vnbaylable ſtrong bandes detaines</l>
               <l>The ſoules of wretched Louers in diſtreſſe,</l>
               <l>tormented midſt a world of endleſſe paines;</l>
               <l>For faire <hi>Proſerpines</hi> ſake, your louelie Queene,</l>
               <l>Heare me recite my ſorrowes yet but greene.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:10897:6"/>
            <lg>
               <l>I That amongſt my Ditties woonted was</l>
               <l>to ſing the motion of eternall heauen:</l>
               <l>How all the Planets in their circles paſſe,</l>
               <l>and at their times make vp their motions euen.</l>
               <l>Muſt change my ſtile, and taught by proofe to ſing,</l>
               <l>Prooue the effect of Loue, a fickle thing.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The ſolitarie wood which I freqnented,</l>
               <l>wheras the <hi>Syluan</hi> Gods admit'd my name:</l>
               <l>Both Gods and woods together haue lamented</l>
               <l>th'v ntimely proofe I taſted of the ſame:</l>
               <l>And all agreeing in my tune doe ſing,</l>
               <l>How Loues effect is an vnconſtant thing.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The whilom deſart plaines where nothing grew,</l>
               <l>now fertill by the meanes my muſicke made:</l>
               <l>Gin now againe for ſorrow to renew</l>
               <l>their olde accuſtomable wearie trade.</l>
               <l>And witneſſe what a cauſe I haue to ſing,</l>
               <l>How Loues effect is an vnconſtant thing.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I loued <hi>Euridice,</hi> the faireſt face</l>
               <l>that euer heauens eie did looke vpon:</l>
               <l>Or euer ſprang from elementall race,</l>
               <l>or euer humaine tence were fixed on.</l>
               <l>Whoſe timeleſſe death with teares make <hi>Orpheus</hi> ſing,</l>
               <l>That Loues effect is an vnconſtant thing.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Vnconſtant Laſſe to him that lou'd thee well,</l>
               <l>made thee Commander of his liues eſtate:</l>
               <l>To leaue him ſo, and chooſe the Prince of Hell,</l>
               <l>and thus reward his loue with thankles hate.</l>
               <l>Thy folly makes me now with ſorrow ſing,</l>
               <l>The effect of Loue to be a fickle thing.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:10897:7"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet to regaine my loſſes come I heere,</l>
               <l>to plead for mercie at grim <hi>Plutoes</hi> ſeat:</l>
               <l>Who when he ſees my waight of woes appear</l>
               <l>and heares me all my ſorrowes to repeat,</l>
               <l>Will in his juſtice ſay, well may I ſing,</l>
               <l>That Loues effect is an vnconſtant thing.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And you the watchfull keepers of theſe ports,</l>
               <l>affoord but me the entrance to thoſe plaines;</l>
               <l>Where euery day ſo many Ghoſts reſortes,</l>
               <l>and I wil for requitall of your paines,</l>
               <l>To heauen &amp; earth, and all their creatures tell,</l>
               <l>How gently I was entertain'd in hell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Wlth this the cruell Porter was content,</l>
               <l>to giue him entra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce through his brazen door:</l>
               <l>Where when he was, the Ghoſtes incontinent</l>
               <l>came flocking ſtill about him more and more.</l>
               <l>And they that whileſt they liu'd had hard his longes,</l>
               <l>For the like pleaſure all of them now longes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To whome the gentle <hi>Thracian</hi> not denies,</l>
               <l>but for the better he might get his right:</l>
               <l>With his accuſtomable harmonies,</l>
               <l>hee gluts their longing ſences with delight:</l>
               <l>And makes them all, both Ghoſtes and Furies ſay,</l>
               <l>Would they might euer more heare <hi>Orpheus</hi> play.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus pleaſantly they paſſe the foremoſt portch,</l>
               <l>and now amongſt the tortures enter in:</l>
               <l>Where ſome in ſcalding mettall frie and ſcortch,</l>
               <l>the tender ſuperficies of their skin.</l>
               <l>Others do freeſe to death, yet neuer die,</l>
               <l>Whoſe paines and liues muſt laſt eternally.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:10897:7"/>
            <lg>
               <l>All theſe and many other torturing kindes,</l>
               <l>the force of his ſweet muſicke did alay:</l>
               <l>And cheer'd againe their now dead drooping mindes,</l>
               <l>that in theſe torments thus tormented ſtay.</l>
               <l>And whileſt he ſung, forgets their former vaine,</l>
               <l>The one his nature, th'other all his paine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then came he neere a place where hee might ſee,</l>
               <l>a gliding ſtreame, that ſwiftly runnes away:</l>
               <l>Ouer whoſe bankes doth hang a broad branch'd tree,</l>
               <l>that with much fruit her boughs to th'earth did ſway.</l>
               <l>Vnder whoſe ſhade in water to the chin,</l>
               <l>Poore <hi>Tantalus</hi> is forc'd to labour in.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ready to ſtarue for food, poore ſoule hee ſtandes,</l>
               <l>and yet the fruite hangs round about his head:</l>
               <l>But when he ſtriues to catch them with his hand,</l>
               <l>they are conuayd from him with ſudden ſpeed.</l>
               <l>And when hee hopes to quench his thirſt with drinke,</l>
               <l>Then doth the water ſettle downe and ſinke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>By him <hi>Ixion</hi> on a torturing wheele,</l>
               <l>continually is rack'd and torne aſunder:</l>
               <l>His bodie yet decayes not any deale,</l>
               <l>but ſtill indures thoſe paines, which is a woonder,</l>
               <l>That being rack'd and tortur'd in this rate,</l>
               <l>His bodie ſhould continue in one ſtate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There lies <hi>Promotheus</hi> faſtened to the ground,</l>
               <l>vpon whole heart a greedy vulture feedes:</l>
               <l>And wher he feeds new flcſh growes in the the wound,</l>
               <l>and ſo his hart and hurt doe dayly breed.</l>
               <l>And <hi>Siſiphus</hi> by him doth make his mone,</l>
               <l>Wearied with labouring vp the tumbling ſtone.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:10897:8"/>
            <lg>
               <l>To whom when <hi>Orpheus</hi> came and gan to ſing,</l>
               <l>their paines ſurceaſt, and they were ſomething eaſ'd:</l>
               <l>Whoſe harmonie effected ſuch a thing,</l>
               <l>as ther withall the Furies ſeem'd well pleaſ'd.</l>
               <l>And all agreed there with one conſent,</l>
               <l>To ſpend that day in hell with merriment.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then <hi>Tantalus</hi> his ſtreame did run no more,</l>
               <l>the tree hung ſtill, and ſtir'd not from his head,</l>
               <l>And he forgot the thirſt he had before,</l>
               <l>and thanked <hi>Orpheus</hi> for his ſo good deed,</l>
               <l>In this releaſing him from that paine,</l>
               <l>Which many years before he did ſuſtaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then <hi>Siſiphus</hi> his rowling ſtone ſtood ſtill:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ixions</hi> paines began for to decreaſe:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Promotheus</hi> Vulture hauing eat her fill,</l>
               <l>from tyring of his heart-ſtrings gan to ceaſe.</l>
               <l>And all the tortures cls that hell containes,</l>
               <l>Did then ſurceaſe their plagues and direſul paines.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And followed <hi>Orpheus</hi> to the Cypres trees,</l>
               <l>vndet whoſe ſhades the wearie Souldiours reſt;</l>
               <l>Who ſorting there themſelues in companies,</l>
               <l>with euerlaſting quietnes are bleſt.</l>
               <l>And in their conterence there again reuiue</l>
               <l>Th'exploytes they did, when as they were aliue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There was old <hi>Priam</hi> and his fiftie ſonnes,</l>
               <l>that for their countries honour were ſuppreſt:</l>
               <l>The Greeks, whoſe names in euery Poem runs,</l>
               <l>there ſpend their quiet dayes in peace and reſt,</l>
               <l>And he whoſe loue did win the <hi>Carthage</hi> Queene,</l>
               <l>Venterous <hi>Aeneas</hi> reſt vpon that greene.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:10897:8"/>
            <lg>
               <l>There gins the Poct once againe relate</l>
               <l>the waightie cauſe that drew him to that place:</l>
               <l>In euerie word lamenting his eſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>that hee was borne to ſuffer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> grace.</l>
               <l>He that had euerie creature at his call,</l>
               <l>Should now ſtand need for to bee help'd of all.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You that haue tri'd (quoth hee) Loues hard euent,</l>
               <l>and the vnconſtant kind of womens ſect:</l>
               <l>And you whoſe time in wearie warres was ſpent,</l>
               <l>which Loue and Louers paſsions did neglect.</l>
               <l>For pittie ſake helpe, for to cure my paine,</l>
               <l>By getting my <hi>Euridice</hi> againe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And in your judgmentes view my heauic plight,</l>
               <l>that haue aduentur'd this ſo dangerous toyle:</l>
               <l>To view the monuments of endleſſe night,</l>
               <l>that yeelds no other thing ſaue rape and ſpoyle.</l>
               <l>And tell mee then, if that for all my paine,</l>
               <l>I bee not woorthy of her loue againe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Your toyles that whilom you ſuſtain'd aboue,</l>
               <l>was pleaſure vnto theſe I here abide:</l>
               <l>And all your dangerous quarrels for your loue,</l>
               <l>compar'd with mine, may all be ſet aſide.</l>
               <l>Yet could the world deuiſe a greater paine,</l>
               <l>I would endure to get my loue againe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My Loue, the ſweeteſt Loue that ere ſuruiued,</l>
               <l>woonder of heauen, and the ſame of earth:,</l>
               <l>Vntimely death vniuſtly hath depriued,</l>
               <l>and would no longer let her heare my mirth.</l>
               <l>For her ſweet ſake what would I not ſuſtaine,</l>
               <l>If I might ſo recouer her againe.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:10897:9"/>
            <lg>
               <l>For Loue thy brother <hi>Iour</hi> for ſooke,</l>
               <l>his glorious high celeſtiall ſeate:</l>
               <l>And to a Feere himſelfe betooke,</l>
               <l>that with his <hi>Daned</hi> hee might treat.</l>
               <l>And did himſelfe confuſe and ſay,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quod Amor vincit omnia.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Apelle,</hi> Learnings greateſt friend,</l>
               <l>for <hi>Daphnes</hi> ſake came from aboue:</l>
               <l>And doted on her, to this end,</l>
               <l>he might on earth enjoy her loue.</l>
               <l>And was the firſt that ere did ſay,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quod Amor vincit ownia.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus Loue that enrers at the ele,</l>
               <l>and ſleely ſteales downe to the heart:</l>
               <l>There doth ingender fantaſie,</l>
               <l>whoſe iſſue breeds, or joy, or ſmart.</l>
               <l>Perforce enforces all to ſay,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quod Amor vincit omnia.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This fancie hath ſet me on fire,</l>
               <l>and furiouſly inflames my breaſt:</l>
               <l>Feeding my ſoule with fierce deſire</l>
               <l>of her whoſe thought denies me reſt.</l>
               <l>And make me ſing both night and day,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quod Amor vincit omnia.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whoſe faire <hi>Idea</hi> thou haſt haſt got,</l>
               <l>To beare <hi>Proſerpine</hi> companie:</l>
               <l>Keeping her cloſe that I might not</l>
               <l>looke on my faire <hi>Euridice,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which now with ſorrow makes me ſay,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quod Amor vincit omnia.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:10897:9"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Shee ſtands thee heere in little ſteed,</l>
               <l>for thou haſt many Millions more:</l>
               <l>Then with her loue ſupply my need,</l>
               <l>and I will ſing thy praiſe therfore.</l>
               <l>And whileſt I liue ſtill will I ſay,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quod Amor vincit omnia.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Plead faire <hi>Proſerpine</hi> for her ſake,</l>
               <l>who in her prime of loue decay'd</l>
               <l>And on her ſome compaſſion take,</l>
               <l>which was a wife, yet di'd a maid.</l>
               <l>For thou knowſt well what joy is bred</l>
               <l>Enjoying of a Louers bed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Fortune and Loue vnconſtant friends,</l>
               <l>agreed vnto our marriage day:</l>
               <l>And furdred all our Loues pretends,</l>
               <l>with what within their power lay:</l>
               <l>Vntill we had both woo'd and wed,</l>
               <l>Then Fortune ſnach'd her from my bed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And in deſpight of Loue detaines,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Euridice</hi> within your power:</l>
               <l>And me afflictes with Louers paines,</l>
               <l>which are increaſing euerie hower.</l>
               <l>Becauſe ſhe knew not what was bred</l>
               <l>Within a Louers loyall bed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In that incloſure breeds delight,</l>
               <l>the pleaſing ſoule of ſweet content:</l>
               <l>Contented beſt to ſpend the night,</l>
               <l>in ſuch ſoule-pleaſing merriment.</l>
               <l>As thou canſt witneſſe well, is bred</l>
               <l>Within a loyall Louers bed.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:10897:10"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Where all <hi>Elizian</hi> ioyes doe dwell,</l>
               <l>incircled there by <hi>Cupids</hi> charmes,</l>
               <l>And more delight then I can tell,</l>
               <l>ingendred in a Louers armes.</l>
               <l>Becauſe I tried not what was bred,</l>
               <l>Within a loyall Louers bed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But that inſtinct of Nature tels,</l>
               <l>the hidden pleaſure of that place:</l>
               <l>Where more delightſome daliance dwels,</l>
               <l>then in the gazing on her face.</l>
               <l>There are the liuelle pleaſures bred,</l>
               <l>That longs vnto a mariage bed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Of this faire marke did <hi>Orpheus</hi> miſſe,</l>
               <l>and loſt the pleaſute of that ſport:</l>
               <l>Been come vnto the gates of bliſſe,</l>
               <l>I could not get into the fort:</l>
               <l>For my <hi>Euridice</hi> was dead,</l>
               <l>Before I could enioy her bed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With this the Poet ouer-cloyd with griefe,</l>
               <l>no ſurther could extend his miſerie:</l>
               <l>But with ſad teares ſeem'd to implore relieſe,</l>
               <l>to rid him from this wofull extaſie,</l>
               <l>At whoſe ſad teares the fearful god did grant</l>
               <l>That he ſhould haue her with this couenant.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In all his wearie iourney vp againe,</l>
               <l>hee ſhould no once looke backe vnto his loue:</l>
               <l>But from the ſpeaking to her ſhould reſraine,</l>
               <l>vntill he came vp to the world aboue,</l>
               <l>Which if he did, then ſhould he all his life,</l>
               <l>Enjoy her bodie as his married wiſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:10897:10"/>
            <lg>
               <l>But if fond jealouſie ſhould make him doubt,</l>
               <l>and he looke backe to ſee his Loues ſweet face:</l>
               <l>Before he were from his vaſt kingdome out,</l>
               <l>and paſt the fatall limmits of that place.</l>
               <l>Then ſhould his wife be ſnatch'd away againe,</l>
               <l>And he ſhould nere the like good tutne obtaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Which curteſie the Poet gentlie tooke,</l>
               <l>and with contentment did accept this thing</l>
               <l>Expecting her with manie a lingring looke,</l>
               <l>the cauſe that drew him the ther for to ſing.</l>
               <l>Till at the length as the grim-God commands,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Euridice</hi> was rendred to his hands.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But intercourſe of ſpeech was there forbidden,</l>
               <l>he might not welcome her with louing words:</l>
               <l>And with a duskie vale her face was hidden,</l>
               <l>that no tranſparance from her eies affoords.</l>
               <l>He was commanded to eſchue the place,</l>
               <l>And ſhe had leaue to follow him apace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus both together theſe two Louers goe,</l>
               <l>with this reſtraint of mutuall conference:</l>
               <l>VVhoſe ſad demeanes the witneſſes of woe,</l>
               <l>ſhew'd diſcontent, but that with patience</l>
               <l>Men muſt of force obey the Gods decrees,</l>
               <l>Though they extend vnto their injuries.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Long thus they traneill'd in this diſcontent,</l>
               <l>Each wiſhing of the other to hane ſight:</l>
               <l>Vntill their iourney now was almoſt ſpent,</l>
               <l>and they might ſee a glimmering of the light:</l>
               <l>For they were wel-nigh come vnto thoſe bounds,</l>
               <l>That parts <hi>Anernus</hi> and the vpper grounds,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:10897:11"/>
               <l>Where jealous thought that in a reſtleſſe mind,</l>
               <l>breeds diſconted paſsions mixt with feate:</l>
               <l>Was vrging <hi>Orpheus</hi> oft to looke behind,</l>
               <l>to ſee if his <hi>Eursdice</hi> were there,</l>
               <l>Vntill remembrance of his promiſe tolde.</l>
               <l>He might not venter for to be ſo bold.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Oſt was his faltring tongue about to ſpeake,</l>
               <l>and call his ſweeteſt Loue by her ſweet name:</l>
               <l>But being halfe afrayd leaſt he ſhould breake</l>
               <l>the Gods beheſts, and ſo incurre his ſhame:</l>
               <l>With much adoe his ſpeaking doth refraine:</l>
               <l>Although (God knowes) it was vnto his paine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But longer can he not forbeare to ſee,</l>
               <l>if ſhee did follow him along or no:</l>
               <l>Such was th'effect of burning jealouſie,</l>
               <l>that would not let him any further goe,</l>
               <l>Before he had ſatisfi'd his longing mind,</l>
               <l>In looking if his louer were behind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And at the length boldly aſſayes to trie,</l>
               <l>turning him backe to her, whom he ſo loued:</l>
               <l>When ſhe was ſnatched from him by and by</l>
               <l>and from his ſight immediatly remooued.</l>
               <l>And he himſelfe left to himſelfe againe,</l>
               <l>Becauſe he did not from this thing refraine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Grieuing to ſee himſelfe thus ouerſhot,</l>
               <l>and all his labour ſort vnto that end:</l>
               <l>Leauing that curſed place, he homward got,</l>
               <l>there fullie bending of himſelfe to ſpend</l>
               <l>The future remnant of his ſingle life,</l>
               <l>In ſcorne of pleaſing Loue, or louing wife.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:10897:11"/>
            <lg>
               <l>And in inuectiue Ditties day lie ſinges,</l>
               <l>th'uncertain pleaſure of vnconſtant Loue:</l>
               <l>How manie woes a womans beautie bringes,</l>
               <l>and into what extreames this ioy doth ſhoue</l>
               <l>Poore fooliſh men, that ere they be awarre</l>
               <l>Will raſhlie ouerſhoot themſelues ſo fatre.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There gins he ſing of ſecrete Loues deceites,</l>
               <l>and womens fawning fickle companie?</l>
               <l>The outward golden ſhew of poyſoned baytes,</l>
               <l>that drawes ſo many men to miſerie.</l>
               <l>And for an inſtance ſets himſelfe to ſhew,</l>
               <l>One that had ſuffred all this pleaſing woe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVhoſe ſonges did ſort vnto ſuch deepe effect,</l>
               <l>as draw mens fancies from thir former wiues:</l>
               <l>VVomens vaine loue beginning to neglect,</l>
               <l>and in the fieldes with <hi>Orpheus</hi> ſpend their liues:</l>
               <l>VVith which ſweet life they ſeem'd ſo well content,</l>
               <l>As made them curſe the former time the'ad ſpent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>At which the women not a little grieue,</l>
               <l>to ſee their conquering Captaine thus ore-botne:</l>
               <l>They gin deuiſe how beſt they might relieue,</l>
               <l>their fading glorie being almoſt worne.</l>
               <l>Which by no meanes they hope for to atchieue,</l>
               <l>As long as <hi>Orpheus</hi> doth remaine aliue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVhich to preuent in ſolemne wiſe they cite,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eir companie together all in in one:</l>
               <l>VVhere euerie buſie head will needs indite,</l>
               <l>a meanes how they might get poore <hi>Orpheus</hi> gone,</l>
               <l>longſt whomeat length the oaſe was thus decid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>that <hi>Orpheus</hi> of his life ſhould be depriued <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:10897:12"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Where jealous thought that in a reſtleſſe mind,</l>
               <l>breeds diſconted paſsions mixt with feate:</l>
               <l>Was vrging <hi>Orpheus</hi> oft to looke behind,</l>
               <l>to ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>f his <hi>Euridice</hi> were there,</l>
               <l>Vntill remembrance of his promiſe tolde.</l>
               <l>He might not venter for to be ſo bold.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Oft was his faltring tongue about to ſpeake,</l>
               <l>and call his ſweeteſt Loue by her ſweet name:</l>
               <l>But being halfe afrayd leaſt he ſhould breake</l>
               <l>the Gods beheſts, and ſo incurre his ſhame:</l>
               <l>With much adoe his ſpeaking doth refraine:</l>
               <l>Although (God knowes) it was vnto his paine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But longer can he not forbeare to ſee,</l>
               <l>if ſhee did follow him along or no:</l>
               <l>Such was th'effect of burning jealouſie,</l>
               <l>that would not let him any further goe,</l>
               <l>Before he had ſatisfi'd his longing mind,</l>
               <l>In looking if his louer were behind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And at the length boldly aſſayes to trie,</l>
               <l>turning him backe to her, whom he ſo loued:</l>
               <l>When ſhe was ſnatched from him by and by</l>
               <l>and from his ſight immediatly remooued.</l>
               <l>And he himſelfe left to himſelfe againe,</l>
               <l>Becauſe he did not from this thing refraine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Grieuing to ſee himſelfe thus ouerſhot,</l>
               <l>and all his labour ſort vnto that end:</l>
               <l>Leauing that curſed place, he homward got,</l>
               <l>there fullie bending of himſelfe to ſpend</l>
               <l>The future remnant of his ſingle life,</l>
               <l>In ſcorne of pleaſing Loue, or louing wife.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:10897:12"/>
            <lg>
               <l>And in inuectiue Ditties day lie ſinges,</l>
               <l>th'uncertain pleaſure of vnconſtant Loue:</l>
               <l>How manie woes a womans beautie bringes,</l>
               <l>and into what extreames this ioy doth ſhoue</l>
               <l>Poore fooliſh men, that ere they be awarre</l>
               <l>Will raſhlie ouerſhoot themſelues ſo farre.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There gins he ſing of ſecrete Loues deceites,</l>
               <l>and womens fawning fickle companie?</l>
               <l>The outward golden ſhew of poyſoned baytes,</l>
               <l>that drawes ſo many men to miſerie.</l>
               <l>And for an inſtance ſets himſelfe to ſhew,</l>
               <l>One that had ſuffred all this pleaſing woe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVhoſe ſonges did ſort vnto ſuch deepe effect,</l>
               <l>as draw mens fancies from thir former wiues:</l>
               <l>VVomens vaine loue beginning to neglect,</l>
               <l>and in the fieldes with <hi>Orpheus</hi> ſpend their liues:</l>
               <l>VVith which ſweet life they ſeem'd ſo well content,</l>
               <l>As made them curſe the former time the'ad ſpent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>At which the women not a little grieue,</l>
               <l>to ſee their conquering Captaine thus ore-botne:</l>
               <l>They gin deuiſe how beſt they might relieue,</l>
               <l>their fading glorie being almoſt worne.</l>
               <l>Which by no meanes they hope for to atchieue,</l>
               <l>As long as <hi>Orpheus</hi> doth remaine aliue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVhich to preuent in ſolemte wiſe they cite,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heir companie together all in in one:</l>
               <l>VVhere euerie buſie head will needs indite,</l>
               <l>a meanes how they might get poore <hi>Orpheus</hi> gone,</l>
               <l>Mongſt whome at length the oaſe was thus deci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>That <hi>Orpheus</hi> of his life ſhould be depriued</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:10897:13"/>
            <lg>
               <l>And thus they all agreed in one conſent,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſome occaſion to procure his end:</l>
               <l>VVhen to the place they flocke incontinent,</l>
               <l>wheras he vſ'd his wofull dayes to ſpend,</l>
               <l>And finding him alone without his traine,</l>
               <l>Vpon him fall they all with might and maine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And with confuſed weapons beat him downe,</l>
               <l>quenching their angrie thirſt with his warm blood:</l>
               <l>At whoſe vntimely death though heauens frowne,</l>
               <l>yet they defend their quarrell to be good,</l>
               <l>And for their maſſacre this reaſon render,</l>
               <l>He was an enemie vnto their gender.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVhich done, to rid him quite out of the way,</l>
               <l>him and his Harpe they into <hi>Hebar</hi> fling:</l>
               <l>Vpon whoſe ſtringes the gliding ſtreames doe play,</l>
               <l>and for his ſoule lamenting Dirges ſing.</l>
               <l>Till to the watrie Oceans greedy wombe,</l>
               <l>They carie him for to go ſeeke his tombe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But then faire heauens in their due regard,</l>
               <l>pittying his end that ſo had ſpent his dayes:</l>
               <l>In juſtice thus his merits do reward,</l>
               <l>vnto their euer memorable praiſe.</l>
               <l>Thus they determin'd all with one conſent,</l>
               <l>For to draw vp his heauenlie Inſtrument.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And place it in that Chriſtall monument.</l>
               <l>the euerliuing regiſtrie of fame:</l>
               <l>The golden ſtartie ſpangled firmament,</l>
               <l>where in remembrance of the Poets name</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> renue his memorie,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> date out liues eternitie.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
